Finding Aid for St. Hilda’s Episcopal Church (River Rouge, Mich.) records, 1918-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
St. Hilda’s Episcopal Church (River Rouge, Mich.) records 1918-2011
St. Hilda’s Episcopal Church (River Rouge, Mich.).
1 oversize volume
5 linear feet
2012174 Ba 2
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated by the Episcopal Church, Diocese of Michigan (donor no. 1059 ) in 2011.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
St. Hilda's Episcopal Church in River Rouge can date its history back to 1897 when several interested families in the area held a meeting in their home. The result was St. Mark's Mission under the care of the Rev. George N. Harris, rector of St. Stephen's, Wyandotte. In 1906 the mission was renamed the Mission of the Advent.
After the mission was well established, the members purchased land on the corner of Genesee and Batavia, where in 1910-1911 the first frame church building was erected. The name St. Hilda's was suggested by a member after his mother church in Hartlepool, England. On November 13, 1921, Dean Warren L. Rogers of St. Paul's Cathedral laid the cornerstone for the new church building, but the new church was not to be. Only the basement section was completed.
In December 1943, the mission became free of debt. Papers of incorporation as a parish were taken out in November 1943 and St. Hilda's was accepted as a parish at the 111th Annual Convention of the Diocese of Michigan in January 1944.
After World War II, the church raised funds on its own without the aid of the Diocese. By April 1953 there were sufficient funds to erect a church building. At this time the old frame building was torn down, and construction of the new brick church began.
Due to declining membership in the 1990s and the first decade of the new century, St. Hilda's ceased operation in 2011.
The records of St. Hilda's have been arranged into the following series: Registers of baptisms, communicants, burials, marriages, etc.; Register of church services; Church governance; Women's Organizations; Membership records; Weekly Bulletins and Programs of Special Events; and Office files.
Subjects:
Episcopal Church--Michigan--River Rouge.; St. Hilda's Episcopal Church (River Rouge, Mich.); Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--River Rouge.; River Rouge (Mich.)--Church history.
- Registers of baptisms, communicants, burials, marriages, etc.
  - July 13, 1925-December 24, 1944 include Communicants, November 1936-December 1942; Baptisms, August 1925-December 1944; Confirmations, December 1925-December 1944; Burials, July 1925-November 1944; Marriages, July 1925-October 1937 (Volume 1)
  - April 27, 1968-May 6, 1979 include Baptisms, November 1971-May 1979; Confirmations, January 1972-May 1978; Marriages, April 1968-February 1979; Burials, January 1971-April 1979 (Box 1)
- Register of church services
  - 2007-2011 (Box 1)
- Church governance
  - Bishop's Committee minutes
    - 1918-1927 (Box 1)
    - 1928-1935 (Box 1)
    - 1936-1940 (Box 1)
    - 1941-1943 (Box 1)
  - Vestry minutes
    - 1948-1950 (Box 1)
    - 1951-1953 (Box 1)
    - 1954-1957 (Box 1)
    - 1958-1963 (Box 1)
    - 1964-1972 (Box 1)
    - 1973-1975 (Box 1)
    - 1976 (Box 1)
    - 1977-1981 (Box 1)
    - 1982-1989 (Box 2)
    - 1990-2002 (Box 2)
    - 2003-2011 (Box 2)
  - Annual Parish Meeting minutes and attachments
    - 1930s-1940s (Box 2)
      (The minutes of the annual meeting were frequently filed with the Bishop's Committee and Vestry minutes during this period)
    - 1954-1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1972 (Box 2)
    - 1972-1984 (Box 2)
    - 1986-1999 (Box 2)
- Women's Organizations
  - Episcopal Church Women
    - Minute book 1970-1973 (Box 3)
    - Annual meeting 1981 (Box 3)
  - Women's Guild
    - Minute book 1944-1945 (Box 3)
  - Altar Guild
    - Annual Reports 1949-1977 (Box 3)
      (some gaps)
    - Minute book 1945-1949 (Box 3)
    - Minute book 1950-1985 (Box 3)
    - Minute book 1986-1998 (Box 3)
    - Minute book 1999-2008 (Box 3)
    - Financial records (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Girl's Friendly Society
    - Newsletter: Twigs 1938-1941 (Box 3)
    - Reports, programs, and miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Membership records
  - Directories (Box 3)
  - Baptism information slips and related material (Box 3)
  - Confirmation information slips (Box 3)
  - Obituary cards (Box 3)
  - Weddings -- Information slips and declaration of intention (Box 3)
  - Acceptance of letters of transfer (Box 3)
  - Mailing lists (Box 3)
  - Membership and address cards (Box 4)
    (in 1 card file box)
- Weekly Bulletins and Programs of Special Events
  - The Parish Record 1925-1929 (Box 4)
  - Weekly bulletins 1982-1983, 1987-2001 (Box 4)
  - Weekly bulletins 2002-2011 (Box 5)
  - Programs for special occasions, 2 folders (Box 5)
- Office files
  - Constitution and by-laws (Box 5)
  - History and anniversary materials (Box 5)
  - Downriver Episcopal Area Ministry (DREAM) (Box 5)
  - Contents of safety deposit box: include deeds, surveys, land contract, and related (Box 5)
  - In Remembrance Book (Box 5)
  - St. Hilda's Church School 1970-1971 (Box 5)
  - Secretary's Book 1976-1978 (Box 5)
  - Photographs (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)